<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A schoole for young souldiers containing in briefe the whole discipline of vvarre, especially so much as is meet for the captaine to teach, or the souldior to learne, that is, to trayne or to be trayned. Fit to be taught throughout England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17387</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121264</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856449</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21999</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21999)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 814:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A schoole for young souldiers containing in briefe the whole discipline of vvarre, especially so much as is meet for the captaine to teach, or the souldior to learne, that is, to trayne or to be trayned. Fit to be taught throughout England.</title>
                  <author>Markham, Gervase, 1568?-1637, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Higginbotham, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Cardnals hat without Newgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Gervase Markham.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Date altered to 1618 in British Library mss-cf. STC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:21999:1"/>
            <head>¶A Schoole for young Souldiers, Containing in briefe the whole Diſcipline of
VVarre, eſpecially ſo much as is meet for the Captaine to teach, or the Souldior to learne, that is, to trayne or
to be trayned. Fit to be taught throughout England.</head>
            <p>Reader for thy better direction obſerue
the courſe of the figures as they ſtand
in order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>To Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
are refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
two
things.
<list>
                     <item>1 Sorting
of armes
which
ſhould be
<list>
                           <item>2 Halfe pikes</item>
                           <item>And halfe ſhot:</item>
                           <item>And the ſhot,</item>
                           <item>Halfe Muskets,</item>
                           <item>Halfe harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſſes.</item>
                           <item>Or two partes
muskets, and
one part
harquebus;</item>
                           <item>The men for
the weapons,
<list>
                                 <item>3 Strongeſt for pikes,</item>
                                 <item>Squareſt for muskets,</item>
                                 <item>Nimbleſt for harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</item>
                                 <item>The armours they
ſhall weare ſhall be
theſe following.
<list>
                                       <item>4 For the pike, a morian, cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
gorget, pouldron, taces,
ſword, girdle, hanger and
pike,</item>
                                       <item>The musket, a morian, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileir,
ſword, girdle, hanger,
bullet, bagge and reſt,</item>
                                       <item>The harquebus, a morian ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilier,
ſword, girdle, hanger,
and bullet bagge:
<list>
                                             <item>Poſtures of the Pike. 15
<list>
                                                   <item>9 order your pike,</item>
                                                   <item>Aduance your pike,</item>
                                                   <item>Set downe your pike</item>
                                                   <item>Shoulder your pike,</item>
                                                   <item>Leuell your pike,</item>
                                                   <item>Slope your pike,</item>
                                                   <item>Port your pike,
<list>
                                                         <item>Charge your pike,</item>
                                                         <item>Check your pike,</item>
                                                         <item>Traile your pike,</item>
                                                         <item>Charge againſt the
right foote and
draw your ſword,</item>
                                                         <item>Charge your pike,
backeward.</item>
                                                         <item>Right to your firſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</item>
                                                         <item>Lay down your pike,</item>
                                                         <item>Take vp your pike.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>5 Formes
of trayning
diuiding e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
into
<list>
                           <item>6 Squadrons</item>
                           <item>Files</item>
                           <item>Fellowſhips: and
then teaching
<list>
                                 <item>7 Cariage of armes,
which muſt be,
<list>
                                       <item>8 Moſt comely, euery ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
weapon, learning theſe
Poſtures following.</item>
                                       <item>10 Vſe of armes,
which muſt be the
<list>
                                             <item>11 Vſe of the pike, in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
or giuing a charge, the
firſt being pike againſt horſe,
the ſecond, pike againſt pike;
vſe of ſhot, is how to preſent
his piece, take his leuell, and
giue his volee.</item>
                                             <item>12 March, in which
<list>
                                                   <item>13 Euery man ſhall obſerue</item>
                                                   <item>his Leader, and them of each
hand, mouing as they moue:</item>
                                                   <item>14 Motion is mouing
<list>
                                                         <item>15 Without
marching
<list>
                                                               <item>16 As turning
on any hand,</item>
                                                               <item>17 Changing
of place,
<list>
                                                                     <item>18 As doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
of rankes
or Files.</item>
                                                                     <item>19 All mouing,
yet none mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,
as
<list>
                                                                           <item>20 Opening
or cloſing
of Ranks or
Files.
<list>
                                                                                 <item>Poſtures of the Musket. 40
<list>
                                                                                       <item>March with the Musket-reſt in the right hand.</item>
                                                                                       <item>March, and with the Musket carry the reſt.</item>
                                                                                       <item>Sinke your reſt, and vnſhoulder your musket.</item>
                                                                                       <item>Hold vp your musket with the right hand, &amp;
let it ſinke in the left:</item>
                                                                                       <item>In the left hand hold your musket, and carry
your reſt with it.</item>
                                                                                       <item>Into the right hand take your match:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Hold well your match between your fingers,
and blow it:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Cocke your match, Try your match:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Blowe your match, and open your panne:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Hold vp your musket, and preſent: giue fire,</item>
                                                                                       <item>Take down your musket, and cary it with the reſt:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Vncocke your match,</item>
                                                                                       <item>Ioyne your match againe betweene your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</item>
                                                                                       <item>Blowe your pan:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Proine your panne, Shut your panne:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Caſt off your panne, Blow off your panne:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Caſt about your musket: Traile your reſt:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Open your charges: Charge your musket:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Your ſcowring ſticke draw out:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Take your ſcowring ſticke ſhorter:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Ramme your powder,</item>
                                                                                       <item>Your ſcowring ſticke draw out,</item>
                                                                                       <item>Take your ſcowring ſticke ſhorter:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Put vp your ſcowring ſticke home;</item>
                                                                                       <item>Bring forward your musket with the left hand,</item>
                                                                                       <item>Hold vp your musket with the right hand, &amp;
recouer your reſt: Shoulder your Musket,</item>
                                                                                       <item>March and carry the Reſt with it.</item>
                                                                                       <item>Vnſhoulder your Musket:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Lay your Musket in the Reſt:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Hold your Musket on the reſt,</item>
                                                                                       <item>Hold your Musket in the Reſt, and with the
left hand only balance.</item>
                                                                                       <item>Take your match into the right hand:</item>
                                                                                       <item>Guard your panne, and ſtand readie.
<list>
                                                                                             <item>Poſtures of the Harquebuſe. 42
<list>
                                                                                                   <item>Shoulder your piece and march:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Vnſhoulder your piece:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>With the right hand hold it vp:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>In the left hand take the piece:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>In the right hand take the match:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Hold well your match and blowe it:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Cocke your match:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Trie your match:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Blowe your match:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Open your panne:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Preſent your piece:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Giue fire:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Take downe the piece, and in the left
hand hold it:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Vncocke your match;</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Ioyne it againe twixt your fingers:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Blowe your panne:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Proyne your panne:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Shut your panne:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Shake off your panne:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Blowe off your looſe cornes:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Turne about your piece:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>To your left ſide let it ſinke:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Open your charges:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Charge your peice:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Your ſcowring ſticke drawe out:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Take your ſcowring ſticke ſhorter:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Ram your powder:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Your ſcowring ſticke drawe out:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Take your ſcowring ſticke ſhorter:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Put vp your ſcowring ſticke home:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>With the left hand, bring forward
the piece:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>With the right hand hold it vp:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Shoulder your piece:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Hold your piece well on your ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
and march:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Vnſhoulder your piece:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>In the left hand let it ſinke:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>With the left hand alone holde the
piece:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>In the right hand take the match:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Cocke your match:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Trie your march:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Blowe off your match:</item>
                                                                                                   <item>Guard your panne and ſtand ready.</item>
                                                                                                </list>
                                                                                             </item>
                                                                                          </list>
                                                                                       </item>
                                                                                    </list>
                                                                                 </item>
                                                                              </list>
                                                                           </item>
                                                                        </list>
                                                                     </item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>21 Sounds of the
drumme, which
is to know,
<list>
                           <item>22 A march,</item>
                           <item>A troope,</item>
                           <item>A charge,</item>
                           <item>A retreit,</item>
                           <item>A call,
The watch,
going to the
mine,</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>soldier</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                     </item>
                     <item>23 Words of direction, which are,</item>
                     <item>24 Leaders, ſtand forward with
your Files,</item>
                     <item>Rankes, open forward, 5 paces:</item>
                     <item>Faces to the right hand,</item>
                     <item>Faces to the left hand,</item>
                     <item>Faces about:</item>
                     <item>turne,</item>
                     <item>Open your Files,</item>
                     <item>Cloſe your Files,</item>
                     <item>Open your files to the right hand,</item>
                     <item>Open your files to the left hand;</item>
                     <item>Cloſe your files to the right hand,</item>
                     <item>Cloſe your files to the left hand;</item>
                     <item>Double your file to the right hand</item>
                     <item>Double your file to the left hand.</item>
                     <item>double your ranks to the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</item>
                     <item>Double your ranks to the left hand</item>
                     <item>As you were:</item>
                     <item>Rancks from behinde cloſe:</item>
                     <item>Ranckes open backward, paces 5.</item>
                     <item>Files on the right hand turne:</item>
                     <item>Rankes on the right hand turne</item>
                     <item>Front paſſe thorow,</item>
                     <item>Followers paſſe thorow,</item>
                     <item>Front as you were,</item>
                     <item>Files as you were,</item>
                     <item>Counter-march to the right hand,</item>
                     <item>Counter-march to the left hand;</item>
                     <item>Caſt off your files to the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</item>
                     <item>Caſt off your files to the left hand.</item>
                     <item>double your front to the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</item>
                     <item>Double your front to the left hand</item>
                     <item>Double your rear to the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</item>
                     <item>Double your reare to the left hand
<figure>
                           <figDesc>soldier</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON
Printed for <hi>Richard Higginbotham,</hi>
and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the
ſigne of the Cardnals hat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Newgate. 161<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
